<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lavvyers philosophy: or, Lavv brought to light Poetized in a diuine rhapsodie or contemplatiue poem. By Roger Tisdale, gent.</title>
            <title>Lawyers philosophy.</title>
            <author>Tisdale, Roger.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841911</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841911</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13791)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 582:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lavvyers philosophy: or, Lavv brought to light Poetized in a diuine rhapsodie or contemplatiue poem. By Roger Tisdale, gent.</title>
                  <title>Lawyers philosophy.</title>
                  <author>Tisdale, Roger.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for I. T[rundle] and H. G[osson] and sold at the widdow [A.] Gossons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Names in imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁴ (-A1, D4, probably blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at foot, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:1"/>
            <p>THE LAWYERS PHILOSOPHY: <hi>OR,</hi> LAVV BROVGHT TO LIGHT. <hi>Poetized</hi> In a Diuine Rhapſodie or <hi>Contemplatiue Poem.</hi> BY ROGER TISDALE, <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sat Serò.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of G. Purslowe; device of an old man standing by an olive tree; above him, on a scroll, the motto, Noli altum sapere (McKerrow 311)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>At London printed for <hi>I.T.</hi> and <hi>H.G.</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:2"/>
            <head>TO THE LEARNED AND REVEREND IOHN DONNE, D. of Diuinitie, Deane of the Cathedrall <hi>Church of</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule <hi>London,</hi> Roger Tiſdale <hi>wiſheth peace of Conſcience</hi> in this world, and the ioy of the <hi>world to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is late: and rather time to lye downe and reſt, then to ſit vp and diſcourſe. The very can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of my life burne dimme, which ſhewes it to bee bed-time. But I know not how, a friend, a deare and dearely
<pb facs="tcp:6527:3"/> reſpected friend, and worthy to bee ſo reſpected,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Vnready Age is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eady for heauen.</note> knockt at the doore, whilſt I was making my ſelfe vnready. No ſooner I heard who it was, but I had <hi>Donne:</hi> left of vntiring my ſelfe, and wiſht rather to tire al my powers, then he ſhould want a welcome. I am now therefore ready againe, but ſo vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ready, as I was inforced to rubbe mine eyes to put off drowzineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could fit my ſelfe to giue him entertainment. Tis you, deare Sir, that after a ſoaring flight of many yeeres, haue now lighted vpon a faire Tree,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cubila quies</note> vnder whoſe branches it is my fortune to hold a poor cottage, (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect (God knowes) to winde and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:6527:3"/> The motion of your wings was to mee a warning of your comming:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Vltimae Muſarum aetas.</note> &amp; though it be in the wayne-time of my life, I could not chuſe but open the doores of my heart to receiue you. To your friends I was heretofore bound in dutie,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obligation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands duty.</note> and (in our youthfull ſocietie) to your ſelfe in loue. But as the times are now, I reioyce that I ſhal haue cauſe to ſhew you both my loue and duty. Flatterie be farre from me, as I wiſh my ſoule from Atheiſme. Yet I muſt ingenuouſly confeſſe,<note place="margin" type="runSum">To obſerue, is a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llable more then to ſerue.</note> as an ancient obſeruant of your worth, that your yong daies were to me of much admiration, as theſe dayes are now of deſerued reuerence. To ſhew ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:6527:4"/> my dutie, it becomes me to meet you with humilitie, as one of the Churches Seruants: and to ſhew my Loue, I haue thought fit to prouide for you ſuch a preſent, as for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I was able to giue, and I know you doe loue pure, and vndefiled <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi> In reſpect of my weakeneſſe, you may call it an Aprill Daiſie, in the Lap of Winter, quickly blaſted: but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of my aſpiring Loue, and your affecting Goodneſſe, I hope it ſhall be receiued and welcomed as a Roſe at Chriſtmas, the New-yeeres gift of Art and Nature.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>its are beſt welcome in Winter.</note> If I haue ſoard into the Sunne, and ſinged my plumes, my fall will be eaſie in your armes. And
<pb facs="tcp:6527:4"/> I hope for the loue of the Muſes (who in your Youth initiated you their Son,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Worthineſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Youth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> venerable.</note> and now in your Age haue elected you a Patron) you will open the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of fauour, and graciouſly giue me your acceptance, with a pardon for my daring into ſo high a Subiect. And as to you in <hi>Capite,</hi> ſo to the reſt in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulo,</hi> I humbly come for acceptance and pardon: as well knowing, you will all thinke better of me, that with <hi>Icarus</hi> I mount high,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Os homini <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lime dedit.</note> and fall into a faire Sea; then I ſhould haue reel'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and falne into a foule Puddle. A Poet that is obſcene forgets his Scene: and I dare promiſe, that if there be any ſpot or blemiſh in
<pb facs="tcp:6527:5"/> this <hi>Poeſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Venus</hi> had a Mole.</note> the fault is not in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, but in the Accident. The blacke Inke may blot the faire paper: and my vnskilfulneſſe miſ-ſhadow the Lawes Beauty. But ſeeing <hi>velle</hi> and <hi>poſse</hi> are not in euery man,<note place="margin" type="runSum">In things lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the will is pleadable.</note> 
               <hi>Eſt voluiſse ſatis</hi> ſhall be my pleading Aduocate. And ſo with my Loue and Duty equally twined together, either into a Lawrell or a Willow Garland (which you pleaſe to account it) I offer it vp with a deſire it were worthy (I will not ſay your beſt, but) any little acceptance: and therewithall reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Moſt obſeruant to your worthineſse,</hi> RO: TISDALE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:5"/>
            <head>TO THE LEARNED AND CONSIDERATE READER. Lege, Perge, Perlege.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Intreat fauour, that you will reade me: &amp; fauour, that you will regard mee. Reade there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and regard, for ſo you will adde ſome grace in the reading: and reade with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, if it bee with regarding. Conniue a little, &amp; ſo you may indulgeate my hopes. I haue in many places of this worke, rather loſt my Rime, then my Reaſon. It is worthy of your pardon, becauſe I confeſſe my fault. As for the ignorant and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate,
<pb facs="tcp:6527:6"/> I will ſpeake to euery one of them no more but thus:
<q>
                  <l>Quem recitas meus eſt,</l>
                  <l>Sed recitando tuus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo commending this my late-borne iſſue, to bee foſtered vnder your fauours, and expecting you will <hi>Socraticam da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re veniam,</hi> in reſpect of my now aged weakeneſſe, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A poore well-wiſher to the Muſes, RO: TISDALE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:6"/>
            <head>THE LAWYERS PHILOSOPHY:</head>
            <l>AWake my Muſe! &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſlumbring trance,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Praeludium.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Lightly ariſe, and on thy wings aduance,</l>
            <l>Thy nimble-ſoaring Spirit, to the Sunne,</l>
            <l>Aboue the Clouds, that yet doe ouerrunne</l>
            <l>Thy bright-ey'd beauty! Rowze away this dream,</l>
            <l>That eddies in thy braine, like to a ſtreame,</l>
            <l>Whoſe giddy windings with <hi>Plebeian</hi> ſtormes,</l>
            <l>Turne, and returne, begetting ſundry formes.</l>
            <l>What though my ſighs like clouds do fill the aire?</l>
            <l>Thinke it not night. Nor let vs ſo duſpaire,</l>
            <l>As fainting to lye downe in ſorrowes deepe,</l>
            <l>And there take vp our laſt eternall ſleepe.</l>
            <l>No, no, ſhake off the dewfals of the Night,</l>
            <l>That dampe thy plumes, and ſoare into the Light,</l>
            <l>With cheerefull notes: whilſt I retir'd ſit ſtill,</l>
            <l>Sighing a ſad <hi>Faburthen</hi> from my quill,</l>
            <l>To thy more nimble warblings. Let not feare</l>
            <l>Diſtract our hopes! there's One aboue will heare,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:7"/>
            <l>If all the world neglect vs. And for rumours,</l>
            <l>Breath'd from the Vulgar, which are only tumours,</l>
            <l>And ſwelling water-bubbles, that together</l>
            <l>Doe riſe, and fall, according to the weather,</l>
            <l>Why ſhould we feare them? Let the inward Man</l>
            <l>Looke vpward, then doe Enuy what ſhe can.</l>
            <l>Set therefore now thy voice in tune to mine,</l>
            <l>In deſcant manner! and againe to thine</l>
            <l>Ile tune a ground: and both together we</l>
            <l>Two parts in one, ſo ſweetly will agree,</l>
            <l>As whilſt the rabble, and rude multitude,</l>
            <l>With their vnciuill clamours doe intrude,</l>
            <l>Breaking all <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> true Muſicks lore,</l>
            <l>We will in tune, them out of tune deplore.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Law, the ſubiect of this worke.</note>The <hi>Law</hi> muſt be our Song: not Pedlers French,</l>
            <l>Nor old Preſcriptions laid vp in the Trench</l>
            <l>Of ruſty Time: Nor moth-eaten Decrees</l>
            <l>Worne out of date: Nor that, whoſe golden fees</l>
            <l>Makes the tongue flow with Arguments of wit,</l>
            <l>And troll apace in Angell-Rethorick.</l>
            <l>Theſe are but wrangling Ecchoes. But the <hi>Law</hi>
            </l>
            <l>We are to ſing of, hath the power to draw</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The worthineſſe of this ſubiect.</note>All <hi>Powers</hi> to Obedience, in Loue,</l>
            <l>And not conſtraint, as being ſet aboue</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:7"/>
            <l>In the Seraphick Spheres of holy Angels,</l>
            <l>Penning the ſongs of Peace, &amp; ſweet Euangels.</l>
            <l>I meane that Law, that was beyond all Time,</l>
            <l>And yet euen now rings forth, ſo ſweet a chyme</l>
            <l>Into our cares and vnderſtanding parts,</l>
            <l>As tunes the World, and glads all vpright hearts,<note place="margin" type="runSum">What this Law is.</note>
            </l>
            <l>It is the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Wiſedome:</hi> whoſe right hand,</l>
            <l>Is that eternall <hi>Power,</hi> that did command</l>
            <l>Of nothing, All-things, in their ſeuerall numbers,</l>
            <l>And all in One brought forth a world of wonders.</l>
            <l>His left hand <hi>Goodnes,</hi> or eternall <hi>Loue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That on the <hi>Chaos</hi> like the ſiluer <hi>Doue</hi>
            </l>
            <l>On <hi>Noahs</hi> watry Deluge ſweetly gliding,</l>
            <l>Of new Diſcoueries brought the happy tiding,</l>
            <l>And form'd all formes, one for anothers ſake,</l>
            <l>And for himſelfe them all as one did make.</l>
            <l>Whilſt in the mid'ſt <hi>Wiſedome</hi> did fit inthron'd,</l>
            <l>Spangled with Starres, and with a crowne adornd</l>
            <l>Of awfull <hi>Maieſtie</hi> writing a Lecture,</l>
            <l>To all his creatures, with that ſacred Scepter,</l>
            <l>Of his iuſt will, whereby he ſets a border</l>
            <l>To euery forme, and giues all formes their order.<note place="margin" type="runSum">This Law is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: Power, Wiſedome, Loue</note>
            </l>
            <l>Of this <hi>Law</hi> muſt I ſing: the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> that from the heau'ny <hi>Tower,</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:8"/>
            <l>On the wide-ſpredding ſixe-wing'd <hi>Cherubins,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Deſcended downe into this frame of things:</l>
            <l>And in ſix dayes ſhed his trine-working Spirit</l>
            <l>Through <hi>All</hi> of this <hi>Round-All,</hi> to diſ-inherit</l>
            <l>Confuſion from his worke, and make faire <hi>Light,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The true ſucceeding iſſue of blacke Night.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">A Poeticall Inuocation.</note>O therefore thou moſt ſacred <hi>Archy-Muſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With dulced, and harmonious Tones transfuſe</l>
            <l>All my beſt Powers! Beare my frailety vp</l>
            <l>The great <hi>Olympian</hi> height! and reach the cup</l>
            <l>Of heau'nly <hi>Nectar,</hi> to my fainting hand!</l>
            <l>That I may taſte, and with that taſte command</l>
            <l>Darke <hi>Chaos</hi> to deſcend, and ſpritely fire,</l>
            <l>From out dead Embers lightly to aſpire.</l>
            <l>That as the Snake by caſting off her Slough,</l>
            <l>The Eagle of his Bill aged and tough,</l>
            <l>Renue their youthfull temper: or more fit,</l>
            <l>As did <hi>Elias</hi> let his garment ſlip,</l>
            <l>Caſting off humane fraileties, when his Spirit</l>
            <l>Kindling with zeale, mounted the burning Charrie</l>
            <l>To <hi>Ioues</hi> bright-ſhining Temple: So my powers,</l>
            <l>Forſaking earths darke Elementall Bowers,</l>
            <l>May nimbly ſoare into th'Angellick Tribe,</l>
            <l>And be with them diuinely ſtellifide.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:8"/>
            <l>Luciferous Beauties, faire,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of Angels.</note> and firſt of creatures</l>
            <l>Light of the prime <hi>Light,</hi> intellectuall features</l>
            <l>Of the firſt Forme, Heau'ns glorious <hi>Architype,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The ſonnes of <hi>Elohim,</hi> and the dayes delight.</l>
            <l>With you I firſt begin to ſhew <hi>Lawes</hi> power</l>
            <l>And calculate the Birth and natiue hower</l>
            <l>Of your great greatneſſe, in whom firſt the <hi>Law</hi>
            </l>
            <l>(As in the firſt of Subiects vnder awe,</l>
            <l>Of heau'ns eternall Scepter) had his <hi>Being</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In golden Thrones, but knew no golden feeing.</l>
            <l>Tis you bright Mirrors of Maieſticke beauty,</l>
            <l>Collecting in your Orbes with ſacred duty</l>
            <l>Th' Ideall Rayes of Him, whoſe all-diſcerning</l>
            <l>Doth make you ſhine with intellectuall Learning.</l>
            <l>Tis you in whom I ſee as in a glaſſe,</l>
            <l>What is to come, what's now, and long ſince was</l>
            <l>Before there was <hi>Beginning.</hi> So the Bell</l>
            <l>Tolles to the Graue: So the cleere Fountaine Well,</l>
            <l>Is by the eddying ſtreames at laſt found out:</l>
            <l>And the celeſtiall eye that wheeles about</l>
            <l>This elementall Square, by his bright Rayes,</l>
            <l>That on the Chriſtall-ſtreaming Riuer playes,</l>
            <l>Is ſtedfaſtly therein diſcern'd and ſeene,</l>
            <l>That elſe by none but <hi>Ioues</hi> own Birds hath beene.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:9"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Homers</hi> golden Chaine: God, Angels, Starres, Elements.</note>And ſo by your tralucent beames of Light,</l>
            <l>Shot from the great Maieſtick Throne of Right,</l>
            <l>Into your dutyous Orbes, and then againe</l>
            <l>From you into the great celeſtiall Maine,</l>
            <l>And Sea of many Beauties, which deſcending</l>
            <l>Into theſe lower parts, that haue depending,</l>
            <l>Onely from things aboue, we reade, and ſee,</l>
            <l>In Charecters of State, and Maieſtie,</l>
            <l>The Law of Power, Wiſedome, and of Loue,</l>
            <l>That doth in all inferiour Subiects moue,</l>
            <l>Creating, Ruling, and withall preſeruing</l>
            <l>Things in their Being, Order, and true ſeruing.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Eſſence &amp; Power</note>Eſſence and Being in this Round of things,</l>
            <l>Shewes the great Power of the King of Kings:</l>
            <l>That could of Nothing ſuch a Something make,</l>
            <l>As doth amaze and cauſe all Powers to ſhake,</l>
            <l>In comprehending but the leaſt Creation</l>
            <l>His Power hath fram'd in this Conglomoration.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Order and Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note>Order ſhewes Wiſedome, ſetting eu'ry part</l>
            <l>With ſuch a ſweet facilitie and Art,</l>
            <l>Each in ſubordinate Order to another,</l>
            <l>As that to this, and this to that is Brother,</l>
            <l>In ſympathy, and correſpondent frame,</l>
            <l>And all together dutyouſly proclaime</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:9"/>
            <l>The God of Order to be onely Wiſe,</l>
            <l>Deſeruing <hi>Hecatomben</hi> ſacrifice.</l>
            <l>But when we looke how eu'ry thing created,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Beauty &amp; Loue.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Is from aboue vs inwardly innated</l>
            <l>With fruitfull Vertues, thriuing qualities,</l>
            <l>That out of their pure Natures doe ariſe,</l>
            <l>All beautious in themſelues, and fit for th'vſe</l>
            <l>One of another: who can other chooſe,</l>
            <l>But ſee, and fairely reade, Goodnes and Loue,</l>
            <l>In this great Volume, written from aboue,</l>
            <l>With Gods owne finger, in ſuch ſweet inditing,</l>
            <l>As if Eternall Loue for his delighting,</l>
            <l>Had pen'd a Poem all of Loue and ſweetneſſe,</l>
            <l>To ſhew himſelfe, and teach vs Loue &amp; meekeneſſe?</l>
            <l>All theſe (and theſe are all, no more but three</l>
            <l>Vnited in one ſacred Vnitie:)</l>
            <l>As Eſſence, Order, Beauty in this Frame,</l>
            <l>And Power, Wiſedome, Loue aboue the ſame:</l>
            <l>Theſe three, I ſay, are the true Rules of Law,</l>
            <l>Before all time, and in all time doe awe</l>
            <l>The creature in his bounds. For what's command</l>
            <l>That wanteth Power? Or who can vnderſtand</l>
            <l>What Power is, without a Being Subiect,</l>
            <l>O're which it hath Dominion to iudge it.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:10"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſedome is Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nny. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſdome without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue, is ſubtilty. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue, without Wiſedome and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower, is folly.</note>Yet <hi>Power</hi> without foreſeeing <hi>Wiſedome</hi> erreth,</l>
            <l>Not knowing: but with cruelty deterreth,</l>
            <l>Where it commands: when <hi>Sapience</hi> ioynd with <hi>Power,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ordreth</hi> extremes, and maketh mildneſſe lower.</l>
            <l>It truely <hi>Gouernes, Wiſedome</hi> is the <hi>Law,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Knowes to inſtruct, and how to keepe in awe.</l>
            <l>But what is all th'eſſentiall frame of things?</l>
            <l>And what is <hi>Order?</hi> Neither of them brings</l>
            <l>Perfection to the worke, without true vſe,</l>
            <l>Which <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Goodnes</hi> ſweetly doth infuſe.</l>
            <l>So in a Clocke we ſee the ſolid forme,</l>
            <l>On many nimble-mouing wheeles is borne,</l>
            <l>All order'd, with ſuch <hi>Order,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Art,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As one to All, and All to euery part,</l>
            <l>Is ſymmetrall, ſhewing the Makers skill,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Power</hi> to make. But ſhould the Makers will</l>
            <l>Haue gone no further, and not motion lent,</l>
            <l>To ſhew the vſe, and his owne faire intent:</l>
            <l>Who could haue call'd that well-fram'd forme a Clocke,</l>
            <l>Or knowne it other wiſe then as a mocke</l>
            <l>Of pow'rfull Art, that wants his proper end,</l>
            <l>Feeding the eye, but doth to nothing tend?</l>
            <l>Will in the maker, tending to direction,</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> is the full perfection,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:10"/>
            <l>Which is true <hi>Loue.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Court Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of Law.</note> And ſo in this round <hi>Sphere</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Finding ſweet <hi>Beauty, Order,</hi> and <hi>Eſſence</hi> there,</l>
            <l>We therewithall from the <hi>Floriferous</hi> Centre,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Floriferous. <hi>2.</hi> Stelliferous. <hi>3.</hi> Luciferous.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Through you <hi>Stelliferous.</hi> Stations ſoone do enter,</l>
            <l>Into your bright <hi>Luciferous</hi> Orbes of Beauty</l>
            <l>(Faire ſonnes of <hi>Elohim</hi>) and there reade the duty</l>
            <l>Of true-borne Subiects, euer held in awe,</l>
            <l>Vnder the Trine-Vne ſoueraigntie of <hi>Law.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whereof that I may ſing, firſt giue me leaue,</l>
            <l>The triple Region of this World to cleaue,</l>
            <l>Iuſt in three parts, as three Court Hals, wherein</l>
            <l>Of Errors they the vpper hand doe winne,</l>
            <l>And in diſpoſing right to euery one,</l>
            <l>Forbid withall, that wrong be done to none.</l>
            <l>The firſt and loweſt is this earthly Stage,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The great Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hath <hi>3.</hi> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </l>
            <l>Whereon we tread in wandring equipage:</l>
            <l>All richly hung about her flowry Stronds,</l>
            <l>With precious Gemmes like Sparkes of Diamonds</l>
            <l>Dropt downe from heauen: and is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Hall</l>
            <l>Where diuers Courts are kept,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Kings Bench. Chancery. Common Plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that vnto All</l>
            <l>Giue common Right, in Earth, in Ayre, in Seas,</l>
            <l>With <hi>Royall, Peacefull,</hi> and with <hi>Common Pleas,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whereof hereafter. But aboue all theſe,</l>
            <l>Aſcending vpward by a few degrees,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:11"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tar-Chamber.</note>One Court in glorious State aboue the reſt,</l>
            <l>Opens her Gates equally Eaſt and Weſt:</l>
            <l>Wherein the Sunne of Maieſtie doth guild,</l>
            <l>Like Aprill Flowers in a Meddowy Field,</l>
            <l>Her ſtarry Thrones of Iudgement. Heere doth ſit</l>
            <l>The Power of Warre, and true <hi>Promethean</hi> Wit:</l>
            <l>The <hi>Iouialiſt,</hi> and grauer <hi>Saturnine:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Milde <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> Doue, and quick-eyd <hi>Serpentine.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In briefe, this Court holds Planetary Station,</l>
            <l>And is the great Star-Chamber Conſtellation.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arliament.</note>Next this, vp higher, throgh heau'ns <hi>Painted Chamber</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>Galaxia</hi> of the great Commander</l>
            <l>Of this round Vniuerſe, a third Court-Hall,</l>
            <l>Sacred for State, and made Imperiall,</l>
            <l>Aboue all others, entertaines the King,</l>
            <l>Crown'd, and inthron'd, vpon whoſe right-hand wing,</l>
            <l>His Sonne the Prince of Peace, in Robes of State</l>
            <l>Sits richly cloth'd. Where that they may debate</l>
            <l>The Kingdomes great affaires (as from them ſent)</l>
            <l>The Breath of Maieſtie cals a Parliament</l>
            <l>Of Angell-Senatours wiſe Intelligences,</l>
            <l>Full of Diuine, and ſacred influences.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Poeticall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eſtie.</note>But ſtay, my Muſe! dar'ſt thou aſpire ſo high,</l>
            <l>On waxen wings? Or dar'ſt thou mount ſo nigh</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:11"/>
            <l>That pow'rfull <hi>Wiſdome?</hi> that <hi>All-ſapient</hi> Power,</l>
            <l>That made yeeres, months, weekes, dayes, &amp; eu'ry houre,</l>
            <l>Yea, eu'ry minute, &amp; times ſmalleſt mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</l>
            <l>To be the Regiſter, and ſtately Comment</l>
            <l>Of his admired workes, and working Spirit?</l>
            <l>Forbeare I ſay! and and either climbe the Charrit,</l>
            <l>Of true Seraphick Loue that doth vnite</l>
            <l>Wiſedome and Power (like a Fauourite</l>
            <l>Of that great King of Kings) or be ſtill mute,</l>
            <l>And humbly kneeling offer vp thy ſute</l>
            <l>Of true Obedience, till that Arme deſcend,</l>
            <l>To lift thee vp, that Vertue doth defend.<note place="margin" type="runSum">A Poeticall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And with the thought me thinkes already now,</l>
            <l>I am all Fire, and I know not how</l>
            <l>The darke confuſed <hi>Chaos</hi> of my braine,</l>
            <l>And all thoſe earthly Powers, that reſtraine</l>
            <l>Mans climing Faculties, in an inſtant are</l>
            <l>Like an inflamed Meteor in the Ayre;</l>
            <l>And what was maſſie, intricate, and thicke,</l>
            <l>Is now become light, deleuer, and quicke,</l>
            <l>To mount through Heau'ns bright ſtarry Regiment,</l>
            <l>Into the higheſt Court of Parliament.</l>
            <l>Where <hi>Power, Wiſdome, Lone,</hi> doe ſit in acting</l>
            <l>Lawes truely good, that ſuffer no detracting.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:12"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Law is all Order and Harmony.</note>Sing then of theſe: and then thou ſing'ſt of all,</l>
            <l>That can within the Scale of Muſicke fall:</l>
            <l>For theſe are Muſicke, and that rauiſhing Tone,</l>
            <l>That from the <hi>Chaos</hi> wrought all things to One,</l>
            <l>And order'd all diſorders with one <hi>Fiat</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of heauenly ſweetneſſe, the true <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>Quiet:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whereto all Vniſons with one conſent,</l>
            <l>As ſtrings are fitted on an Inſtrument,</l>
            <l>Doe ſeu'rally in tune and order riſe,</l>
            <l>And altogether ſweetly harmonize.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Moſes <hi>Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               </note>In the <hi>Beginning</hi> — O where am I now?</l>
            <l>Eu'n at an ending. For my Muſe doth bow</l>
            <l>In Circle-wiſe, whoſe firſt and laſt is One</l>
            <l>And All in All, that neuer is alone,</l>
            <l>And yet all One. In this <hi>Beginning</hi> was it,</l>
            <l>When (but Eternitie) none did ſurpaſſe it,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Trine Elohim</hi> created Heau'n and Earth,</l>
            <l>And to this <hi>Round-All</hi> gaue a timely Birth,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Chaos confuſedly deſcribed.</note>Vntimely though it ſeem'd. For darkneſſe then</l>
            <l>Surrounded All this <hi>Round-All,</hi> eu'n as when</l>
            <l>A Point confuſ'dly multiplide, doth cloud</l>
            <l>The Virgin paper, whilſt the Artſman proud</l>
            <l>Of his inacting Power, doth blot it ouer</l>
            <l>All blacke, intending after to diſcouer,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:12"/>
            <l>Lines, Bodies, Shapes, &amp; ſundry beauteons formes,</l>
            <l>Drawne out of darknes, as faire Peace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtormes,</l>
            <l>And Day from Night. For in this darke Abyſſe,</l>
            <l>Heau'n, Earth, and all therein contained is</l>
            <l>Confuſedly in one Conglomoration</l>
            <l>Were ſymboliz'd as ſeeds of this Creation.</l>
            <l>But in ſuch ſtrife, and orderleſſe diſorder,</l>
            <l>As therein nothing had his proper border,</l>
            <l>But each did Warre, to haue anothers place,</l>
            <l>And fight to giue, or get vnknowne diſgrace.</l>
            <l>That in the ſmooldring heate, cold Earth &amp; Water,</l>
            <l>In dogged wrangle, did bring forth a Daughter,</l>
            <l>Call'd the tempeſtuous Ayre. And Aire and Fire,</l>
            <l>Piercing the <hi>Chaos,</hi> did themſelues retire,</l>
            <l>Into the Centreleſſe boſome of the Deepe,</l>
            <l>And through by-crannies heere and there did creepe,</l>
            <l>Till at the laſt, ioyning their lawleſſe forces,</l>
            <l>To ſtirre vp Warre, like two vntamed Horſes,</l>
            <l>They ſhook with tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pling all the formeleſſe Maſſe,</l>
            <l>And with that Ague-fit did boldly paſſe</l>
            <l>Through euery humour, eu'ry qualitie</l>
            <l>Of heate and cold, drought and humiditie,</l>
            <l>That altogether in an vprore were,</l>
            <l>Yet to be ſought out, no man could tell where:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:13"/>
            <l>For yet there was no place: but high and low,</l>
            <l>Was all inforcement, none his place did know.</l>
            <l>Which was the cauſe, turmoyle and hurly-burly</l>
            <l>Roſe like a tempeſt, and each thing was ſurly</l>
            <l>Vnto another, without giuing way,</l>
            <l>But proudly iuſtling, and inforcing ſtay</l>
            <l>That as at Sea, when <hi>Aeolus</hi> vnbindes</l>
            <l>The muſtring clouds, &amp; ſends contrarious winds,</l>
            <l>To rouze the fretful waues: a ſulpherous thunder</l>
            <l>With ſmoaky Lightning breakes the Aire aſunder,</l>
            <l>To meete thoſe raging Tidelings, and together</l>
            <l>All ioyne in conflict, forcing ſtormy weather,</l>
            <l>That doth not cloud, but darke this Hemiſphere,</l>
            <l>And in a graue tranſparent Light interre:</l>
            <l>Saue that vpon the liquid Ocean glaſſe</l>
            <l>The nimble Lightning now &amp; then doth paſſe,</l>
            <l>And giues a a glim'ring light, which who had ſeene it,</l>
            <l>He could no more but as a twinkling deeme it.</l>
            <l>So in this vndigeſted formeleſſe Matter,</l>
            <l>Strife and Contention forcing vp the Water,</l>
            <l>A ſmoaky breath, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out their ſulph'rous bowels,</l>
            <l>In dusky clouds, and ſtormy vapour rowles,</l>
            <l>Heere, there, and all about, that with the fogge</l>
            <l>So forced from that deepe and myery Bogge,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:13"/>
            <l>Cymerian Darknes was that nothing-All</l>
            <l>And All-beginning Nothing: ſaue withall,</l>
            <l>That by odde ſtarts, and ſuddainties, ſometime</l>
            <l>In this hot tumult, from the muddy ſlime,</l>
            <l>A liquid ſweate vpon the vpper face</l>
            <l>Of the vaſt Deepe (like Pearle or Iſinglaſſe)</l>
            <l>Did iſſue forth, caſting a gleaming ſpangle,</l>
            <l>Which by and by, thicke darknes did intangle.</l>
            <l>But now behold!<note place="margin" type="runSum">God moued vpon the face of the Waters.</note> (for now 'tis worth an <hi>Ecce</hi>)</l>
            <l>When all was formeleſſe, void, and in perplexie,</l>
            <l>Darke, and obſcure, the Spirit of <hi>Elohim,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>On the moiſt Superficies did ſwim,</l>
            <l>Nay (as the Text ſaith) incubat, and neſsle,</l>
            <l>To brood the vnborn, who as then did wreſtle</l>
            <l>Together in the teeming wombe of Nature,</l>
            <l>Who ſhould be firſt, and who of higheſt ſtature.</l>
            <l>And all this in the darke: for Darkneſſe ſtill</l>
            <l>The ſpacious Vault of Emptineſſe did fill.</l>
            <l>And he that was chiefe Lord of this Creation,</l>
            <l>Had Darkneſſe made his ſecret habitation.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Darknes is Gods Habitation. <hi>Pſal. 18.</hi>
               </note>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecret I call it; for what quick-ey'd ſence</l>
            <l>Of the beſt Sophiſt, euer found from whence</l>
            <l>Or how darke <hi>Chaos</hi> came? or could diſcouer</l>
            <l>What formleſſe Matter was, though much they houer,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:14"/>
            <l>As I doe now about it? Then much leſſe,</l>
            <l>Can the dull eye of Art, ſee or expreſſe</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Light inacceſsible</note>The <hi>Light</hi> that dims all <hi>Lights.</hi> Gaze on the Sun,</l>
            <l>And thou ſhalt finde thine eye-ſight quite vndone,</l>
            <l>Strucken with endleſſe Darknes. So much rather,</l>
            <l>Who in his Eſſence ſeekes to know the Father</l>
            <l>Of all created <hi>Lights,</hi> glorious beyond</l>
            <l>What either Men, or Angels vnderſtand,</l>
            <l>May in that ſearch ſay to the Day, good Night,</l>
            <l>And liue for euer a blinded Sodomite,</l>
            <l>Dwelling in darkneſſe. For when all is done,</l>
            <l>That nimble wit, and quicke conception</l>
            <l>Can pry into, we doe but grope, and feele,</l>
            <l>Like cupſhot Bacchinals, that wandring reele</l>
            <l>About the roome, to finde a burning Candle,</l>
            <l>Which in the darke themſelues doe hold &amp; handle,</l>
            <l>And cannot ſee it. Feare, and admiration</l>
            <l>Beſt fits a wiſe and ſober generation,</l>
            <l>In this inquirie. Whoſo ſeekes, doth well,</l>
            <l>For that great <hi>Light</hi> that doth in darkneſſe dwell.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">God is Light and Life.</note>The Diuine Eaglet that did towre ſo high</l>
            <l>Into this <hi>Light,</hi> aboue the Starry skie,</l>
            <l>Found him to be the very Life of all,</l>
            <l>Within this new-created generall.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:14"/>
            <l>And that this <hi>Life</hi> was <hi>Light,</hi> which by diuine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And ſacred influence, did pierce and ſhine,</l>
            <l>Eu'n through the <hi>Chaos,</hi> in the ſecret darke,</l>
            <l>And yet withall, he leaues it for a marke</l>
            <l>Of eminence, and much to be commended,</l>
            <l>That <hi>Light</hi> of darknes was not comprehended.</l>
            <l>Againe, the ſixe-wing'd ſacred <hi>Cherubim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.</note>
            </l>
            <l>The knowing ſonnes of this great <hi>Elohim,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Prime ſchollers of the prime <hi>Light,</hi> and endowed</l>
            <l>With learned graces, haue their eyes yet ſhrowded,</l>
            <l>With their two fore-wings, ſhewing baſhfull feare,</l>
            <l>And humble reu'rence to that Light ſo cleere:</l>
            <l>Which ſhould it in full Maieſtie forth ſhine,</l>
            <l>And they gaze on it with wide open eyne,</l>
            <l>Thoſe bright-ey'd <hi>Lampes</hi> would ſoone in darknes</l>
            <l>Whom now he doth with oyly graces cheriſh.</l>
            <l>Therefore, O Man! and thou my forward Muſe!</l>
            <l>Dare not too high! leſt we our ſelues abuſe.</l>
            <l>An humble knowledge makes vs to aſcend:</l>
            <l>Pride caſts vs downe, vnfit to comprehend.</l>
            <l>So that to know the <hi>Light,</hi> with true diſcerning,</l>
            <l>Is to confeſſe it comes not in our learning.</l>
            <l>For if that we could comprehend that <hi>Light,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Not it, but darknes ſhould be infinite.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:15"/>
            <l>Yet that we might not altogether liue</l>
            <l>In lawleſſe darkneſſe, and our Spirits giue</l>
            <l>Vp to dull ignorance, as nothing knowing,</l>
            <l>Of this prime Light, behold, new light comes flowing</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">A Parliament of Power, Wiſdome, Loue.</note>From the bright Fountaine. <hi>Power, Wiſdome, Loue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In conſultation being ſet aboue,</l>
            <l>How to reduce darke <hi>Chaos</hi> into forme,</l>
            <l>And giue a Law vnto the lawleſſe ſtorme</l>
            <l>Of the firſt then vnformed Elements,</l>
            <l>Shot nimble Lightning forth, and ſo preuents</l>
            <l>The rage of rude diſorder. Darknes fell,</l>
            <l>Affrighted downe into the depth of Hell:</l>
            <l>And with the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Wiſedome, Fiat Lux,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Law of Light.</note>Light flowing came, in a moſt glorious flux.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Let there be Light!</hi> O, was there euer Law</l>
            <l>So ſhort, ſo ſweet? or had more power to awe</l>
            <l>Confuſed ſtrife? when all was out of frame,</l>
            <l>This was the Law, did reconcile the ſame:</l>
            <l>Proclaim'd a Peace: gaue eye-ſight to the blinde:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Light threefold.</note>And droſsie Oare in Minerals refinde.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Peace</hi> is the ſong of Angels. Light of Eye,</l>
            <l>The faire tranſparent beauty of the Skie.</l>
            <l>In Elements, the Fire hath ſupreme power,</l>
            <l>The ſcumme and Tartar of the reſt to skowre,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:15"/>
            <l>To purge, and quicken. So in a three-fold Light,</l>
            <l>The Day-ſpring riſeth, baniſhing the Night:</l>
            <l>The Night of lawleſſe Error, and of blindneſſe;</l>
            <l>Of warlike ſtrife, and turbulent vnkindneſſe:</l>
            <l>That ſees not what is what: but in confuſion,</l>
            <l>All Law-rights breakes, with violent intruſion,</l>
            <l>One on anothers necke, confounding Peace,</l>
            <l>And wanting Loue, and ſo without increaſe.</l>
            <l>This Night, I ſay, was baniſht. And the Day,</l>
            <l>The Light, and Law of things, as freſh as <hi>May,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Came like a Bridegroome forth in bright attire,</l>
            <l>As the Meridian Sunne, that doth aſpire</l>
            <l>The Vertick Point. No ſhadow then was ſeene;</l>
            <l>Nor the celeſtiall Curtaine drawne betweene</l>
            <l>This Elementall and the ſupreme Light,</l>
            <l>Whoſe round Expanſion cloſeth in the Night:</l>
            <l>But All was all alike, and eu'ry where,</l>
            <l>About the earth, tranſparent, bright, and cleere:</l>
            <l>For All was Light. Only in ſite and place,</l>
            <l>There was ſome diff'rence. That had higheſt grace,</l>
            <l>That neereſt to the Prime Light was aduanced,</l>
            <l>And that of leſſe, that towards this Centre chanced.</l>
            <l>The middle Region did of both partake:</l>
            <l>Yet but One Light th'Eternall Power did make,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:16"/>
            <l>To light vs into darkneſſe, there to ſee</l>
            <l>The ſacred Light of all Eternitie.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Law-rights</hi> obſeru'd, doe ſhew vs what is right:</l>
            <l>And Light it is that doth diſcouer Light.</l>
            <l>Truth ſeekes no corners, there doth darknes lurke:</l>
            <l>And mighty <hi>Elohim,</hi> when he fell to worke,</l>
            <l>Lighted a Candle vp that all might view him:</l>
            <l>For <hi>In lumine ſuo videbimus Lumen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The Light creating, by created Light,</l>
            <l>Is out of darkneſſe brought into our ſight.</l>
            <l>For had not Light ſtrooke Darknes vnder-ground,</l>
            <l>How in the darke could any thing bee found,</l>
            <l>That now we finde, and ſee? How could the Law</l>
            <l>Haue come to light? who could Eſſentialls draw</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Number. Order. Vnity.</note>Into their ſeu'rall Numbers? who could order</l>
            <l>Thoſe numbers right? and giue a proper border</l>
            <l>To eu'ry ſuch Eſſentiall? Who (I ſay)</l>
            <l>Could of theſe two finde out the ready way,</l>
            <l>And Number make with Order ſo agree,</l>
            <l>As both ſhould hold one vſefull ſympathy?</l>
            <l>This Light and Law can do. The Law of Light,</l>
            <l>And Light of Law, that giues to all things Right,</l>
            <l>Can Number, Order, and Vnite in One,</l>
            <l>With <hi>Fiat Lux:</hi> for ſo the Law begunne.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:16"/>
            <l>Let there be <hi>Light!</hi> Heere is a word of Power,</l>
            <l>Beyond all Powers: an inriching Dower,</l>
            <l>Beyond all Riches: and they both together,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Law Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding and forbidding</note>
            </l>
            <l>Are a Commandement, well I know not whether</l>
            <l>Commanding, or forbidding. In the meane,</l>
            <l>Wiſedome took place, and being apt to gleane</l>
            <l>Wealth from the One, and Power from another</l>
            <l>Commanded this, and did forbid the tother.</l>
            <l>So Light was cheriſht, and dull darkneſſe chidden:</l>
            <l>Truth brought to Light, &amp; Error was forbidden.</l>
            <l>In briefe this Law in Power being ſtrong,</l>
            <l>And rich in Loue, becauſe it doth no wrong,</l>
            <l>Grew vpright Wiſe: for Wiſdome is the Light</l>
            <l>To Power and Loue, and thereby makes all right.</l>
            <l>So that a new-borne Iſſue from aboue</l>
            <l>Deſcended out from Power, Wiſedome, Loue:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Law deſcended from Heau'n.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And was no ſooner borne, but by and by</l>
            <l>Was entertain'd with gladſome melody.</l>
            <l>And eu'ry one ſung out this cheerefull <hi>Salto,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>I am noua Progenies Coelo demittitur alto.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg. Eclog. 4.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And this was Law: the Law that lighteth All</l>
            <l>Into the Light, and Darknes doth inthrall</l>
            <l>In chaines below the Deepe: ſtrikes Error blind:</l>
            <l>And the light way to Truth &amp; Right doth finde.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:17"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Law of Light inacted.</note>Nor onely ſo: for with the promulgation</l>
            <l>Of this great Law, iſſued a Proclamation,</l>
            <l>Commanding as it went to each degree,</l>
            <l>This lowd proclaiming Summons, <hi>Let there be!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Let,</hi> is a word of <hi>Power: There</hi> ſhewes the place:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Be,</hi> is all <hi>Being, Order,</hi> and due <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And altogether with one <hi>Let there be!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Giues vs faire Light, for eu'ry one to ſee.</l>
            <l>And with that Light, doth ſummon, &amp; conuent,</l>
            <l>In Heau'n, Aire, Earth, a Royall Parliament,</l>
            <l>Of pow'rfull, wiſe, and gracefull Senators,</l>
            <l>True Lamps of Light, and Chriſtall-ſhining Mirrors,</l>
            <l>Who with that Word of Power no ſooner had</l>
            <l>Their due creating ſummons, but all glad,</l>
            <l>Of ſuch a Birth-right, to that word of might,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Light threefold: Intellectuall, Celeſtiall, Elementall.</note>Humbly did Eccho forth, <hi>Let there be Light!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Light Intellectuall in th' Angellick Manſion,</l>
            <l>Celeſtiall Light within the faire Expanſion:</l>
            <l>And in theſe Elementall Orbes downe lower,</l>
            <l>A Light of Fire, to cheriſh, not deuoure.</l>
            <l>And ſo as Light, by Light created was,</l>
            <l>From thoſe true Lights, an Act of Light did paſſe,</l>
            <l>Approu'd in all three Courts, and by the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Eſtabliſht as an euerlaſting thing,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:17"/>
            <l>Not to be darkned: for this Light was ment vs,</l>
            <l>To be a Law, to which <hi>Le Roy aſſentus:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And therefore is enacted vnto All,</l>
            <l>Not to be broke, but held perpetuall.</l>
            <l>Thus was there Light: which in the firſt Creation</l>
            <l>Commanded was vvith Royall approbation.</l>
            <l>Light had not onely Being, but Command</l>
            <l>Was laid vpon that Light, that it ſhould ſtand</l>
            <l>Still in the wayes of Light. Light muſt be Light,</l>
            <l>Not ſtooping downe to the Errors of the Night,</l>
            <l>But hold dependance on the Word of Truth,</l>
            <l>That made this Light, and ſtill this Light renu'th.</l>
            <l>This <hi>Light</hi> thus made, &amp; this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mmandment giuen</l>
            <l>Behold vpon the glorious Thrones of Heau'n,</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Elohim,</hi> the Ancient of Dayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And Father of Lights, did himſelfe vp-raiſe,</l>
            <l>To ſit and view the bright reſplendent beauty</l>
            <l>Of this firſt worke, and with what awfull dutie,</l>
            <l>Each ſeu'rall Lampe ſhone in his proper Sphere,</l>
            <l>About his Palace, either dimme, or cleere,</l>
            <l>And what their Station was.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.</note> Then <hi>Elohim</hi> ſaw</l>
            <l>The Lights he made, and this commanding Law</l>
            <l>Were good. And ſo from out the euening <hi>Chaos,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>(That he no longer might in darkneſſe ſtay vs)</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:18"/>
            <l>He brought the Spring-light of a cheereful morne,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">With Light were Angels created.</note>And with that Spring-light, was the firſt day born.</l>
            <l>Then in the Vpper Houſe incontinent,</l>
            <l>Of this ſo great and Royall Parliament,</l>
            <l>Aſſembled was before the dreadfull Throne</l>
            <l>Of Heau'ns Maieſtick State, a beautious Zone</l>
            <l>Of many Lampes, round-ſhining in a Ring</l>
            <l>Taking their Light from their creating King:</l>
            <l>And ſhooting forth that Light in cheerfull beames,</l>
            <l>To glad this lower world, like dewy ſtreames,</l>
            <l>That from the dropping clouds ſweetly abound,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Seraphim. Cherubim. Thrones.</note>And fruitfull make the dry and barren ground.</l>
            <l>There ſhone Seraphick Loue: and there againe,</l>
            <l>Cherubick Wiſedome: and that ne'r doth wayne,</l>
            <l>Stayd Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſat on Thrones of heau'nly <hi>Light,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With Loue &amp; Wiſdome iudging what was <hi>Right.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And theſe in Number, numberleſſe did ſhine,</l>
            <l>In ſeu'rall Orders: but with ſuch Diuine</l>
            <l>And ſacred Beauty farre aboue the reſt,</l>
            <l>As that in place, both higheſt, and the beſt,</l>
            <l>Theſe did before the ſacred Trinitie,</l>
            <l>Stand forth the prime-elected <hi>Hierarchy.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Dominations.</note>Next in the middle Order, Rule, and Power,</l>
            <l>Without all ſeruile Feare: and then the Flower</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:18"/>
            <l>Of all faire Vertues, euer preualent,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Vertues. Poteſtates.</note>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vndaunted Fortitude:</hi> with whom forth went</l>
            <l>True <hi>Potent Magiſtracie,</hi> ord'ring both,</l>
            <l>That neither Tyran Cruelty nor Sloth</l>
            <l>Had any place: this middle diſtribution,</l>
            <l>Receiu'd all power, and gouern'd by infuſion.</l>
            <l>The laſt and loweſt (if in Heau'n there be</l>
            <l>Place, high and low, as there is of degree)</l>
            <l>Are three Diuine executory Graces</l>
            <note place="margin" type="runSum">Principalities. Archangels. Angels.</note>
            <l>Of warlike power in their ſeu'rall places,</l>
            <l>Leading forth Armies, Legions, Regiments,</l>
            <l>To guard faire Truth, and front all darke Euents.</l>
            <l>Whereof ſome held prime Principalitie,</l>
            <l>As Generall Leaders in Authoritie,</l>
            <l>Some intermediat Officers aduiſing,</l>
            <l>And through the royall campe Archangelizing,</l>
            <l>By Order from aboue: Whilſt all the reſt</l>
            <l>Of this ſo glorious Armie ſtand addreſt,</l>
            <l>Ready to doe, and fairely execute</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Elohims</hi> will, not making ſlowe diſpute.</l>
            <l>Thus was Heau'ns Palace hung with ſhining Lamps:</l>
            <l>And thus about great <hi>Elohim</hi> incampes</l>
            <l>This Royall Hoaſt of Lights: whom could wee ſee,</l>
            <l>And well diſtinguiſh each in their degree,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:19"/>
            <l>What glory were it? But what glory more</l>
            <l>Were it to ſee the euerlaſting dore</l>
            <l>Of Heau'n ſet open, and behold within</l>
            <l>Vpon his Thrones the mighty <hi>Elohim,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Shining in Maieſtie, like a flame of Fire,</l>
            <l>Brighter then is the Sunne? His whole attire</l>
            <l>Collucent like himſelfe? And from his voice</l>
            <l>Iſſuing a floud of Fire? And then the choice</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Nine precious Stones, alluding to the nine orders of Angels. Ezech. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note>Of thoſe Eternall Lights like beautyous Stones</l>
            <l>Set in fine gold, ſhining about thoſe Thrones?</l>
            <l>The fiery <hi>Carbuncle,</hi> and <hi>Topas</hi> greene?</l>
            <l>The <hi>Diamond,</hi> the <hi>Berill,</hi> and <hi>Sardine?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The many-colour'd <hi>Iaſper?</hi> and the <hi>Saphin</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That caſteth forth a bright reſplendent Azur?</l>
            <l>And amongſt others, not to ouerpaſſe</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Smaragdus</hi> and the golden <hi>Chryſopras?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Theſe to behold with an inabled ſight,</l>
            <l>And how each Lampe giues to another Light,</l>
            <l>And all doe from that heauenly <hi>Fiat</hi> take,</l>
            <l>That firſt did light them, and their beauties make,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Light ſet in Iudgement.</note>Were glory beyond greatneſſe. But to ſee,</l>
            <l>The King of Lights ſit in his Maieſtie,</l>
            <l>Commanding Light &amp; Truth: and with what awe</l>
            <l>Thoſe Lights receiue that firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding Law</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:19"/>
            <l>Of Light and Truth: and what melodious order,</l>
            <l>In caſting forth their beames, they keep to further</l>
            <l>Each one anothers Light; as in a Quire</l>
            <l>Of many Tones, ſome low, ſome meane, ſome higher,</l>
            <l>Each Voice doth grace another, and all ſing</l>
            <l>A rauiſhing Antheme to the heauenly King,</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Wiſedome, Power, Loue, Iod, Iah, Iohoue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The Law of Light and Truth that raignes aboue.</l>
            <l>This were a ſweet melodious Rhapſodie,</l>
            <l>T'inchant the Soule in Diuine Extaſie.</l>
            <l>But yet againe, what meanes you riſing Cloud,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The fall of <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> from Light.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And ſmoakie Vapour? what's that noiſe ſo lowd?</l>
            <l>As if ſome mayne Battallion were to ioyne,</l>
            <l>And Souldiers ſtriue to rapine and purloyne?</l>
            <l>What horror doe I ſee? Is darkneſſe yet</l>
            <l>Brought once againe out of the vaſty Deepe,</l>
            <l>And Light in mourning clad? Or topſey-Turuy</l>
            <l>Is all reduc'd to the firſt Hurly-burly</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Chaos,</hi> and Confuſion? O my Muſe!</l>
            <l>Recline that ſoaring compaſſe thou didſt vſe,</l>
            <l>And ſtoope thy flight! New ſtormes begin to riſe</l>
            <l>And humble wings beſt then do fit the wiſe.</l>
            <l>O ſee <hi>Ben-ſchachar</hi> that Luciferous Beauty!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 14.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Sonne of the Morning! and bright Lampe of duty!</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:20"/>
            <l>No ſooner plac'd in Glory, but anon,</l>
            <l>Elated in himſelfe, he ſtands vpon</l>
            <l>His owne proud worth, and with indignitie</l>
            <l>Shootes at the face of Heau'ns great Maieſtie,</l>
            <l>His ſwift-aſpiring Beames: Nor onely ſo:</l>
            <l>But ſtraight he doth a daring Trumpet blowe</l>
            <l>To all the Hoaſt of Heau'n, proclaiming Warres,</l>
            <l>And that he meanes to mount aboue the Starres</l>
            <l>Of mighty <hi>Elohim,</hi> and there alone</l>
            <l>Exalt and raiſe himſelfe vpon his Throne,</l>
            <l>Vpon the holy Mount, and place his worth,</l>
            <l>Within the skirts and confines of the North.</l>
            <l>Nay more then ſo: he venters vp ſo nigh,</l>
            <l>As he will riſe eu'n vp to the moſt High,</l>
            <l>And there be like to him. Then at the ſound</l>
            <l>There was a murmure heard, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> paſſed rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</l>
            <l>Through thouſand Legions of Light-bearing Powers,</l>
            <l>Who ſhould firſt ioyn with him ſo proudly towers.</l>
            <l>And many of thoſe <hi>Lucifers</hi> tooke part,</l>
            <l>To leaue dependance, and to climbe by Art.</l>
            <l>O how on earth can euer things be eu'n,</l>
            <l>When there's ſo ſoone Rebellion raiſ'd in Heau'n?</l>
            <l>But that All-ſeeing Law-giuer that made him</l>
            <l>So great a Light, found darkneſſe to inuade him,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:20"/>
            <l>And compaſſe in thoſe <hi>Centaures</hi> of the Night,</l>
            <l>That were before the beautious dayes delight.</l>
            <l>And he that would not ſtand within the wayes</l>
            <l>Of Light and Truth, nor ſpend eternall dayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 24. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 28.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Amidſt thoſe precious ſhining Stones of Fire</l>
            <l>That Gods delightfull <hi>Eden</hi> doth attire,</l>
            <l>Like Lightning downe from his aſpiring fell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And with his Angels was ſhut vp in Hell:</l>
            <l>In Hell, that but till then was not created,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Hell created in Darkneſſe.</note>
            </l>
            <l>But was a place of Darkneſſe ſituated,</l>
            <l>Farre off from Light: in which a Mooriſh water</l>
            <l>Like ſlimy Pitch, &amp; a blacke ſulph'rous matter</l>
            <l>Left in the <hi>Chaos</hi> (when Heau'ns <hi>Spagiriſt</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Extracted Light, and form'd it as him liſt)</l>
            <l>Were moulded vp together. And till then</l>
            <l>Was nothing elſe within that darkſome Fen.</l>
            <l>But then, eu'n with the fall of daring pride,</l>
            <l>The breath of Maieſtie did ſwiftly glide</l>
            <l>Into the Deepe, and in his anger kindle</l>
            <l>Combuſtious matter, which himſelfe did mingle,</l>
            <l>Of purpoſe to bring forth eternall Fire,</l>
            <l>To puniſh ſinne that proudly durſt aſpire</l>
            <l>To breake the Law of Light. Then ſmoky fume</l>
            <l>Choakt vp Snuf-lights, becauſe they durſt preſume,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:21"/>
            <l>With a few flaſhes and vnſauoury vapors</l>
            <l>To take the place of euer-ſhining Tapers.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Law executed.</note>Pride that would mount, and had not to aſpire,</l>
            <l>Was tumbled down, and puniſht in this Fire.</l>
            <l>So he that was <hi>Ben-ſchachar,</hi> ſonne of Light,</l>
            <l>Was now <hi>Ben-ſchechor,</hi> ſonne of eternall Night.</l>
            <l>Thus was Sinne puniſht: and ſinnes great accuſer</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 36.</note>Did <hi>Tophet</hi> then prepare for the Seducer,</l>
            <l>Smoking with <hi>Aetna</hi> breath. Law kept his power,</l>
            <l>And ſtrooke him downe that ment aloft to tower,</l>
            <l>And chain'd him in (for falling from the Light)</l>
            <l>In chaines of darkneſſe, deepely out of ſight.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">An alluſion.</note>So haue we ſeene Ambition in great Peeres,</l>
            <l>Corruption in falſe Scribes, and Chantocleers,</l>
            <l>That ſing before the Daylight ſongs of peace,</l>
            <l>Not for the Truthes ſake, but for rich increaſe,</l>
            <l>Haue often climb'd to high and great eſtate,</l>
            <l>And in a twinkling been precipitate.</l>
            <l>They left the wayes of Light not being wiſe,</l>
            <l>And tooke their pathes vpon the ſlippery Ice:</l>
            <l>So let them fall. For 'tis not mine intent</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Starre-Chamber.</note>To ſummon any to the Parliament:</l>
            <l>Nor to diſcouer in the great Starre-Chamber</l>
            <l>What are Eclipſes, and what ſignes of danger:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:21"/>
            <l>The dogged humour of dull <hi>Saturnes</hi> motion,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ioues</hi> banquetting, and feminine Deuotion:</l>
            <l>The ſwearing Art of Warre, nor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> luſt,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mercurian</hi> fraud, that findes but little truſt:</l>
            <l>Nor Moone-ſhine Flattery neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant prouing,</l>
            <l>But as the wind and weather cock ſtill mouing:</l>
            <l>'Gainſt none of theſe will I preferre a Bill,</l>
            <l>Leſt they demurre vpon't, for want of skill,</l>
            <l>In drawing vp the Booke, and ſo get coſt,</l>
            <l>With an Attachment, for my labour loſt.</l>
            <l>But thou great Prince of Stars, the faire delight!<note place="margin" type="runSum">The King is the Life of the Law.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Of Heau'n and Earth, in whom the Lord of might</l>
            <l>Hath plac'd his Tent, &amp; built his Tabernacle,</l>
            <l>That Euiternally ſhall ſtand a miracle,</l>
            <l>To all the gazers eyes, and glad the eares</l>
            <l>Of Muſicall inquirie! front my feares</l>
            <l>With thy moſt cheerefull Beames, and make me bold,</l>
            <l>With Eaglet eyes thy beauty to behold!</l>
            <l>In thee the Fountaine is of worth and Power,</l>
            <l>To giue true beauty both to high and lower:</l>
            <l>Of Wiſedome for to guide in all thy Station</l>
            <l>Th' aſpects of Starres in eu'ry Conſtellation:</l>
            <l>And of true Loue and Goodnes (Muſicks Lore)</l>
            <l>Wherewith thou doſt great <hi>Elohim</hi> adore,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:22"/>
            <l>And cheriſh others. Strike the golden wire</l>
            <l>Of thy moſt ſweet, and learned-ſounding Lire,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 38.</note>And all the Morning Starres ſhall daunce and ſing,</l>
            <l>At their vpriſing vnto thee their King.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Magiſtrates.</note>
               <hi>Saturne</hi> ſhall caſt his melancholly off,</l>
            <l>And daunce iudiciall Reuels. <hi>Ioue</hi> ſhall doff</l>
            <l>His proud attire, and leaue light heel'd <hi>Lauoltos,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To cloath himſelfe in bounty, and tread <hi>Saltos</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Worthy his Noble worth. <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall no more</l>
            <l>Weakeneſſe depopulate, nor oppreſſe the poore:</l>
            <l>But hand in hand ſhall willingly aduance</l>
            <l>The Fatherleſſe and Widdow in this daunce.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall change her Luſt for fruitfull Loue,</l>
            <l>And tread a conſtant meaſure: <hi>Mercury</hi> proue</l>
            <l>No ſerpentine Deceiuer, but abound</l>
            <l>In wiſe and witty footings at this Round.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Trencher Flies.</note>As for <hi>Lunarian Changelings</hi> that depend</l>
            <l>Onely vpon the Light thy Lampe doth lend,</l>
            <l>And wax and waine, as to and fro thy Light,</l>
            <l>Doth come or goe, not ſhining but by Night,</l>
            <l>In darkneſſe for their owne aduantage ſake,</l>
            <l>And not in publike: what elſe can we make</l>
            <l>Of them but Antikes, or ſtrange Mimick Apes,</l>
            <l>That in our daunce can put on any ſhapes,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:22"/>
            <l>And yet be nothing?<note place="margin" type="runSum">Theſe doe liue, by Giue giue</note> Theſe I feare me much</l>
            <l>Will take, but what is giuen to others, grutch:</l>
            <l>And neuer ſhall the Muſicke of thy Harpe</l>
            <l>Make them keepe Scene, but they'll or beg or carp.</l>
            <l>Beware of theſe! For were theſe ſet in tune,</l>
            <l>The Flowers of May, each one might crop in <hi>Iune,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And eu'ry one haue ſome. When one hath all,</l>
            <l>How can our daunce in perfect meaſure fall?</l>
            <l>The Country Swaine leaues gleanings on his land,<note place="margin" type="runSum">A Country con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</note>
            </l>
            <l>To helpe the needy. And with foote and hand</l>
            <l>It is a daunce worth looking on to ſee,</l>
            <l>How buſily each one doth keepe degree</l>
            <l>To gather what is left. Heere one doth borrow</l>
            <l>A little from the Sheafe: this in the furrow</l>
            <l>Takes what is ſcatter'd: that the Cart attends:</l>
            <l>Another binds vp at the headlands ends:</l>
            <l>And all at Night goe cheerefully away,</l>
            <l>And daunce together a Harueſt Roundelay.</l>
            <l>Truſt not diſſembling Fire-drakes that caper,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Some things ſeem and are not.</note>
            </l>
            <l>As if they knew to daunce, yet are but vapor,</l>
            <l>Seeming of fiery temper, but are cold,</l>
            <l>And a poore Nut-ſhell will their ſubſtance hold.</l>
            <l>Play not to them! <hi>Pans</hi> Muſicke is moſt fit,</l>
            <l>When <hi>Midas</hi> hath more auarice then wit.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:23"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Sunne of Maieſtie in his Starre-Chamber.</note>But leaue we theſe! And from the Suns diurnall,</l>
            <l>That wheeles a foure &amp; twenty houres iournall,</l>
            <l>Let vs obſerue how on th' Eclipticke Line,</l>
            <l>He progreſſe makes, along from Signe to Signe,</l>
            <l>Caſting his Beames of Maieſtie ſo farre</l>
            <l>As from the loweſt to the higheſt Starre,</l>
            <l>Guiding their wandring <hi>Eccentricities,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And crowning them with faire felicities</l>
            <l>He is the Monarch there. His Law is Light:</l>
            <l>And where he goes, he baniſheth the Night.</l>
            <l>Darkneſſe muſt not controll ſtelliferous Powers,</l>
            <l>Nor come within the high celeſtiall Bowers,</l>
            <l>To All he giues himſelfe. Light is his name,</l>
            <l>And through his Court faire Light hee doth proclaime;</l>
            <l>The only Law that neuer breedeth warres</l>
            <l>Twixt Peeres &amp; People, wandring &amp; fix'd Starres:</l>
            <l>But all is Loue &amp; Peace. Where darkneſſe dwels</l>
            <l>Is Feare begot, then Hare, then nothing elſe</l>
            <l>But blacke Eclipſes wraſtling to preuaile,</l>
            <l>And darken Light within the Dragons tayle.</l>
            <l>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we hide the Light, keep truth vnknown,</l>
            <l>And tread the pathes of Error of our owne:</l>
            <l>What hope is there of Peace? Light is the Law,</l>
            <l>Keepes the cheekes baſhfull, &amp; the Heart in awe.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:23"/>
            <l>Deſcend we now the high Star-Chamber Court,</l>
            <l>And let vs to the lower Hall reſort;</l>
            <l>Where throngs of Creatures, like to clyents preſſe,</l>
            <l>With ſhouldring forwardneſſe to ſeeke redreſſe</l>
            <l>Of ſome darke errours that eclipſe their Light,</l>
            <l>And cloud the Truth to take away their Right.</l>
            <l>Earth, is the Common-place,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Court of Common Pleas</note> in which are fixt</l>
            <l>All Actions, Reall, Perſonall, and Mixt.</l>
            <l>As where things made are of a Simple Nature</l>
            <l>Such as the Elements; there the Creature</l>
            <l>Claimes Reall Intereſt,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reall actions.</note> and enters Plea</l>
            <l>To hold his Birthright, by the rule and ſway</l>
            <l>Of the Predominant. And where we finde,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Perſonall actions.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Thoſe Elements are altred in their kinde,</l>
            <l>And for our vſe with Powers ſo innated,</l>
            <l>As th' Elements become Elementated,</l>
            <l>Each in his proper place: if any faction</l>
            <l>Doe riſe amongſt them,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Mixt actions.</note> there lyes a perſonall action.</l>
            <l>But of all bodies decompoſited,</l>
            <l>Out of thoſe Elements, and by Nature bred;</l>
            <l>What quarrels doe ariſe, receiue their Tryall,</l>
            <l>By Action, part Perſonall, part Reall,</l>
            <l>As mixt of both. And thus is euery Caſe</l>
            <l>Begunne and ended in the Common-Place.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:24"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Court of Kings Bench.</note>The <hi>Kings</hi> high <hi>Bench</hi> is the tranſparent <hi>Aire,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Where Light inthroned in a golden Chaire,</l>
            <l>Shoots forth his Eye-beames brighter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our fire,</l>
            <l>And yet vnſeene makes all the World admire.</l>
            <l>This ſtrikes the Centre with his piercing power,</l>
            <l>Cheareth vp queachy coldneſſe, giues a Dower</l>
            <l>To Natures Treaſurie, is the Life of things,</l>
            <l>And vertue addes to Plants, and Chriſtall Springs.</l>
            <l>In briefe, this is chiefe Iuſtice of the Court,</l>
            <l>Vnder the Prince of Lights, who ſendeth forth,</l>
            <l>And giues him his Commiſsion, to ſit downe,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Pleas of the Crowne.</note>And try before him matters of the Crowne:</l>
            <l>Such as Eclipſe the Maieſtie of Light,</l>
            <l>And vaile faire Truth with Vapours of the Night.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Worthleſſe aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note>So in the Aire, we ſee oft-times aſcend</l>
            <l>Darke foggy miſts, which mounting in the end</l>
            <l>Neare to the Seate of Iuſtice, angry breath</l>
            <l>Flyes from the Iudge, and ſtrikes them to the earth.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Politick aſpirers.</note>Sometimes againe, a farre more ſubtle Vapor,</l>
            <l>Proudly aſpiring to be made a Taper,</l>
            <l>At the celeſtiall Altar: by and by,</l>
            <l>Is fir'd, and ſhot, like Lightning from the Sky.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Traitrous aſpirers</note>Another, but of ſome more viſcous matter,</l>
            <l>Raiſing himſelfe, from Fens, and Mooriſh water;</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:24"/>
            <l>Is hang'd vp in the ayre, and ſet on fire,</l>
            <l>A wonderment for all men to admire.</l>
            <l>Thus is their Treaſon iudg'd, and puniſht right,</l>
            <l>That ſtriue againſt the Maieſtie of Light.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Court of Chancery.</note>
            </l>
            <l>But ſee, the <hi>Halcyon</hi> ſmoothneſſe of the Sea,</l>
            <l>Smiling vpon me, whilſt the Sunne doth play,</l>
            <l>And caſt a cheerefull blandiſh on the waues,</l>
            <l>To welcome All, that of their bounty craues,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Equity. Goodneſſe.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And ſtand in need. The barren thirſty ground</l>
            <l>Doth with their Spring-tides fruitfully abound,</l>
            <l>And brings forth large increaſe. The lympid ayre</l>
            <l>Is vapourized with a moiſture rare,</l>
            <l>And ſubtle in the riſing, to refreſh</l>
            <l>The breathing noſtrils of all liuing fleſh.</l>
            <l>This Court (in briefe) is milde, and bountifull,</l>
            <l>To ſupply wants:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Contempts, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable.</note> though ſomtimes Ships do Hull</l>
            <l>At randome on her waues, for want of skill,</l>
            <l>Or for defection in the Stearemans will,</l>
            <l>Not knowing when it is for ſafety good,</l>
            <l>To beare vp Sayle, or Anchor in the Floud</l>
            <l>If this doe happen, then contemptuous Windes</l>
            <l>Make the Court angry, and the Clyent findes</l>
            <l>But little fauour. This Ship at a ſtay,</l>
            <l>Sticks in the Sands. That making ſwifter way,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:25"/>
            <l>For common Law-rights, is attached backe,</l>
            <l>And Fleetes the Surges to his vtter wracke.</l>
            <l>Another Sailes, with full gale on the Tide,</l>
            <l>Yet in the Deepe, his laſt decree doth hide.</l>
            <l>More I might ſay! Some Ships at Anchor lye</l>
            <l>Doing iuſt nothing: and then by and by</l>
            <l>The Court commands the <hi>Halſer</hi> to be cut,</l>
            <l>And to the Land they are diſmiſt, and put,</l>
            <l>To ſeeke their Fortunes to their grieuous coſt,</l>
            <l>Since idly they their Anchor-hold had loſt.</l>
            <l>Some others neere the Shore doe lye at Roade</l>
            <l>Waiting the Winde: and ſpend in that aboade,</l>
            <l>More then an <hi>Indian</hi> Voyage, All they haue;</l>
            <l>And then <hi>In forma pauperis</hi> doe craue,</l>
            <l>To paſſe the Port, and cannot be admitted,</l>
            <l>To Launch the Deepe, being ſo Shallow-witted:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Chancellour.</note>Till at the laſt, great <hi>Neptune, Chancellour</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of theſe extreames, begins to ſhew his power,</l>
            <l>With a <hi>Quos Ego,</hi> brandiſhing his Mace,</l>
            <l>Wherewith he calmes the Courts tempeſtuous face.</l>
            <l>And ſo when ſtormes had well-nigh ouer-duckt vs,</l>
            <l>Thus made he ſilence: <hi>Praeſtat componere fluctus?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And all was huſht, Then rounded in a Ring,</l>
            <l>The peacefull waues did daunce, and ſweetly ſing</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:25"/>
            <l>About this earthly Stage,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Equity tempers, but not controls the Law.</note> the Centre-Court</l>
            <l>Whereto all Sub-celeſtiall formes reſort</l>
            <l>For common Law-rights, which are ſtrict and graue,</l>
            <l>But temper'd, and made milde, with eu'ry waue,</l>
            <l>That daunceth on the ſhore. The gentle Springs,</l>
            <l>And chryſtall Riuolets; all freely brings,</l>
            <l>From the great Ocean, fruitfulneſſe, and Plenty,</l>
            <l>To eu'ry Creature. Want doth ne'r goe empty,</l>
            <l>Without a ſweet, and ſoueraigne ſupply</l>
            <l>Of that great Ocean-Court of Chancerie.</l>
            <l>But whither am I led? O tell me whither?<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Percloſe.</note>
            </l>
            <l>(Great <hi>Archy-Muſe,</hi> and pow'rfull Law-giuer,</l>
            <l>In all theſe Courts) vnto what ſettled Port</l>
            <l>Shall I now ſteere, and make my laſt reſort?</l>
            <l>Shall I? O ſhall I ſteere into the Mayne?</l>
            <l>And launch the Deepe of Law, that doth ordaine</l>
            <l>In eu'ry Court a ſettled Rule and Order?</l>
            <l>Shall I teach men what is the proper border</l>
            <l>Circumferenceth eu'ry Court? and how</l>
            <l>Obedience to Sou'raigntie doth bow?</l>
            <l>This were a taske, fitting ſome youthfull Merit,</l>
            <l>Whoſe vigour ſhewes a braue Mercurian Spirit.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Saturne</hi> in me is too predominant,</l>
            <l>And retrograde withall. My bloud doth want</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:26"/>
            <l>
               <hi>Caſtalian</hi> moiſture, and <hi>Phebean</hi> fire,</l>
            <l>To <hi>Iuuenize</hi> my Muſe, that ſhould aſpire</l>
            <l>So great a height. My breath goes thicke and ſhort,</l>
            <l>As weary of this iourney. Little Sport</l>
            <l>Were it to climbe <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> in mine Age,</l>
            <l>Or with the Muſes daunce in equipage.</l>
            <l>The ſonnes of Learning well might thinke mee iolly:</l>
            <l>But ſure they would deride my doting folly.</l>
            <l>Therefore I now deſcend, and flagge my plumes</l>
            <l>Low to the ground, whereon my Muſe aſſumes</l>
            <l>Her ſettled reſt. Some other time perchance</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Promethean</hi> fire may ſtirre me to aduance</l>
            <l>A ſecond, and a more aſpiring flight</l>
            <l>That ſhall deſcry the Maieſtie of Light,</l>
            <l>And Law of eu'ry Court. Till when I ceaſe,</l>
            <l>And with a tongue-tide ſilence hold my peace:</l>
            <l>As one that longs to heare what he hath done,</l>
            <l>In lighting vp this Candle in the Sunne.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:26"/>
            <head>To the deſire of my Youth, and hope of mine Age, my young <hi>ſonne</hi> ROGER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Sonne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Commend the reading of this Poem vnto thee, that in it, thou mayſt firſt ſee me what I am: and then learne what I wiſh thee to bee. Make not Poeſie thy profeſsion, but thy pleaſure. Profit ſo gotten, is merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and ends in baſeneſſe. But if for thine own ſolace, thou ſing to thy ſelfe the ſongs of the Muſes, thou ſhalt find ſome <hi>Philomels</hi> will record to thy Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. In thy Verſe bee not wanton, but warie Looſe Numbers, argue light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: and diſcretion is the Badge of Wiſedome. Doe not Critically abuſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6527:27"/> what thou canſt not amend: neither flatteringly ſublime, what thou ſeeſt to be vile. Be thy ſelfe: and bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in thy ſelfe: but take heede that thou be ſeldome leſſe, and neuer more then thy ſelfe. Humilitie is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Baſe, nor Proud. Tis a Poeticall fault, to preſume, and compare. If at any time thou doe ſo, let it bee with thine Equals. For Superiours wil cruſh thee, and Inferiours diſgrace thee. Learne this, till I haue occaſion to teach thee more. And ſo I leaue thee to Gods bleſsing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy louing Father, <hi>R. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6527:27"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
